So this week, my wife and I disagreed as
to what flavor I was going to make. She
wanted gingerbread cookie dough and I
wanted something else. So this week I'm
actually going to make gingerbread
cookie dough. [music]
[music]
Yep. I didn't think this was going to go
any other way. So gingerbread. I hated
gingerbread for years [music] and then
all of a sudden something happened and I
like it. It's um you know a seasonal
flavor, but we're going to make a really
delicious slightly spiced vanilla ice
cream base custard style this time
because I got some egg yolks in the
fridge and I want to use them up. So,
this is going to come with the flavors
of molasses and some seasonal spices as
well, along with a beautiful texture
gingerbread cookie dough that we're
going to make from scratch. So, my mouth
is watering already. What are we going
to need? So, for the ice cream base, you
are going to need 458 g of whole milk.
That's 3.25%.
g of 33 to 35% cream, 65 g of egg yolks,
115 g of sugar, 17 g of glucose or corn
syrup. You can use either. Golden syrup
will also work really well. 45 g of skim
milk powder and 26 g of molasses, not
black strap molasses. It's too bitter
and should be saved for savory dishes.
On to the spices, you're going to need
six grams of ground ginger, four grams
of cinnamon, 1 gram of nutmeg, half a
gram of ground cloves, 1 gram of salt,
and finally 10 g of vanilla extract. The
nutritional breakdown for this recipe is
going to be on Patreon and available to
YouTube members as well. So, if you want
to support the channel, head over to
Patreon or become a YouTube member.
Really helps out. Don't forget to like
and subscribe. Hit that notification
bell as well. It really helps this
channel grow. This is just me doing
this. I don't get any help from anyone
else from the making, filming, and the
editing. So, I need all the help I can
get. So, that's the ice cream base. The
gingerbread cookie dough. What are we
going to need for that? So, we are going
to need 100 g of heat treated allpurpose
flour. That's plain flour elsewhere. 40
g of softened butter. 50 g of brown
sugar. 25 [snorts] g of molasses, 10 g
of milk, and then our spices. 2 g of
ground ginger, 1 g of cinnamon, 0.3 g of
nutmeg, 0.1 g of ground cloves, half a
gram of salt, and 2 g of vanilla. We're
going to start by making that
gingerbread cookie dough. So, let's get
everything out and get started.
[bell]
Right, so the first thing we're going to
do is heat treat our flour. So, our oven
is coming up to temperature 175 200
Fahrenheit, something like that. So, 70
centrade is the recognized temperature
to heat treat flour to kill off any kill
off any pathogens in the oven. Keep an
eye on it. Normally takes about 10
minutes to do this. We're trying to get
all of this flour up to at least 70°
centigrade. Ignore the amount. I'm doing
a double batch. So, in the description
is all the ingredients you need and
the oven's ready. So, flour goes in. So,
now that our flour is preheating, we're
going to deal with our brown sugar and
our butter. We're going to get a bowl
and in all of that goes
butter and our brown sugar. And we're
going to cream this together. Just going
to do it by hand. It doesn't need to be
crazy. Brown sugar will always have
lumps just because of how the molasses
bonds the the the actual sugar crystals
together. If you want to sieve that
brown sugar first, get rid of the lumps.
Makes life much easier to cream. Anyway,
in here we're going to add our molasses
and our salt.
vanilla extract. You can use kind of as
much as you want here, but it really
doesn't need a lot. We're just trying to
boost the flavor of that somewhat. This
is Mexican vanilla. It's from a local
company actually in Calgary.
It's really good stuff. So, with all of
that in there, we're going to just mix
this together and wait for our flour to
be done. As far as spices are concerned
for gingerbread, they are the same
spices that I used for pumpkin spice.
So, I've got a blend in here of the
cinnamon, nutmeg, ginger, cloves, etc.
So, I'm going to use this,
a doublesized batch here.
Plus, I want it to be quite strong
because uh you know, when you bite into
one of those gingerbread cookie dough
lumps, you want that flavor, don't you?
You don't want it to taste nothing. So
in that goes. If you prefer heavier
cinnamon or nutmeg or ginger then go for
that. Obviously ginger bread has more
ginger flavor in the spices than pumpkin
spice which is more cinnamon. That's
basically the difference. So with that
in there, that in there, let's wait for
our flour to be ready. So we go 70°.
Again, do what's right for you. do
what's right for you regarding heat
treating flour. So, just stirring that
around for a couple of minutes. We've
cooled it down to 50°. Still more than
hot enough to melt our butter, but I
just want to get it in. So, 200 g. We're
going to start off with
I keep mixing matching the numbers. I'm
making a double size batch here. So, I'm
making double of everything. So, I just
said 200 grams. It's not. It's 100
grams. So, pay attention to the numbers
that I said earlier on in the video or
in the description. Ignore me. I'm a
rambling old fart. We're just going to
gently mix that in together until we've
added all of the required amount of
flour
into here. Still quite warm.
Thankfully,
I have asbestos hands. So, in there we
go. Let's just combine all this. It
might look like it's going to be quite
dry, but we've not finished yet. We're
going to add some liquid to it in a
second. Once we've mixed our
gingerbread, cookie dough basically
together. We need to just add a little
bit more liquid. Now, you can use milk
if you want, which is the more
traditional thing to use for cookie
dough. That's absolutely fine. I'm going
to boost the ginger flavor with
gingerbread syrup.
Monin make this. Maison Routan, they
make this. Loads of people make
gingerbread syrups. Um, Fabri obviously
is my favorite brand. It's actually not
the best gingerbread syrup, but there
you go. So, we're gonna add enough just
to give this the texture that we want.
So, in the recipe here on this video,
it's 10 ginger
breiness. And we're just going to bring
that together. You can use your hands.
This is balanced so that it doesn't go
solid as a rock in your ice cream. It's
still got a nice chew to it. So, quick
clean up. So, there's a couple of ways
to do this, but the easiest way I found
is to take a seasonal silicon mat. It
has to be seasonal, obviously. And we're
going to
dump that out on there. And you can, if
you want to use a rolling pin and just
smooth that out. Heat treated flour.
Just going to sprinkle that over our
rolling pin.
Get this rolled out. You can make this
any shape you like. Just cut it up into
whatever you like. That's now going to
go in the freezer or the refrigerator
just to harden off. Bring it down. Then
it's a bit more manageable. Let's do the
ice cream base.
So again, I'm making a big old fat batch
of this. Uh full ingredients and amounts
in the description. So, in here, we've
started with our milk, and we're going
to add our other ingredients. So, we're
going to start with our corn syrup. I'm
going to use corn syrup as opposed to
glucose syrup this time.
Going to add in our egg yolks.
All right, let's weigh out our sugar.
Into the sugar, we're going to put the
skim milk powder
in there. And we're going to put some of
our molasses in there. And then our
spices. Again, use as much or as little
as you want. We're going to do two
different types of vanilla. Going to go
with our Mexican vanilla and our vanilla
powder. So, I'm going to get this on
heat. You're going to need to mix it,
whisk it, stir it, whatever you want to
do. Make sure those eggs don't stick to
the bottom. That's really what you're
stirring it to avoid it doing. If the
egg yolks stick to the bottom, they'll
burn and then they'll turn to scrambled
egg. So, keeping those egg yolks moving
while it's heating up stops that
happening. So there we go. Let's pop in
the rest of our ingredients.
So in we go with our salt and then our
vanilla extract.
Vanilla bean powder is optional. Uh I
think it's a great ingredient to have in
the cupboard because you can boost that
vanilla flavor without affecting any of
your recipes. Just going to break up our
vanilla bean seeds. Final ingredient. I
don't know why I got rid of that. Here's
our cream.
And then in a container we go.
But we're just going to leave this in
the refrigerator for about an hour. Then
we can start assembling. Let's get our
ice cream churning away.
[music and bell]
>> [music]
[music]
[bell]
>> We're going
up.
[bell]
[music]
>> [bell]
>> Breakfast time. Gingerbread cookie dough
ice cream smells delicious and I am
looking forward to trying this one.
The gingerbread cookie dough is perfect.
Delicious flavor. That cookie dough
straight out of the freezer. Soft enough
to chew. Doesn't go super super hard.
Really nice gingerbread flavors coming
through. That molasses really coming
through as well, which is delicious.
So, I hope you enjoyed this video.
Seasonal gingerbread cookie dough.
Thanks very much for watching. Don't
forget to like and subscribe and I'll
see you next time.
>> [bell]